<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<title>
Communalism Wiki
</title>
<link>

</link>
<description>
Communalism and Social Ecology
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Wed, 24 Jan 2018 07:43:51 -0500
</lastBuildDate>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<item>
<guid>
/posts/2018-01-24-democratic-confederalism/
</guid>
<link>
/posts/2018-01-24-democratic-confederalism/
</link>
<title>
A Struggle for Freedom: Rojava, Democratic Confederalism and Social Ecology
</title>
<description>
 &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From ISE board member and UMass graduate student Eleanor Finley:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; I recently had the opportunity to visit Turkey and North Kurdistan. In that short time, Istanbul celebrated the third year anniversary of Gezi Park, the Democratic Union Party (HDP) won unprecedented political representation in the Turkish parliament, and the cantons of Cizire and Kobane were joined. Throughout these dramatic events, I was often sitting cross-legged on living room floors, drinking tea and listening to the stories of journalists, activists, and families who had participated in the Rojava Revolution. Such conversations were made possible through many comrades, most of all through Sherhad Hemmi, who acted as a guide, translator, and intellectual companion. Through my travels, I was given a glimpse of the relation between the Kurdish freedom movement and the philosophy of social ecology. By the same token, I gained a much clearer sense of the extraordinary scope and meaning of this particular revolutionary struggle.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;reviving&amp;#95;politics&quot;&gt;Reviving Politics&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Social ecology is a coherent Leftist vision that underscores the potential for human beings to play a mutualistic and creative role in natural evolution. We can fulfill this potential, social ecology argues, by uprooting the irrational, hierarchical, and ecologically-destructive society we currently live under, and by replacing it with a socially-enlightened and ecological society. An essential feature of such a society would be the Aristotelian notion of politics, that is, the direct management of towns, cities, and villages by the people who live there. In other words, social ecology maintains that we can supplant capitalism and the state with a global federation of directly-democratic municipalities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Left-libertarian thinker Murray Bookchin invented and elaborated on social ecology from the 1960s until his death in 2006. However, many other education projects, publishing ventures, political organizations, and writers also constitute this intellectual movement. Social ecology groups exist in many countries- including Turkey, Norway, Spain, Greece, Columbia, the United States and others. Although marginal on the Left as well as the mainstream, social ecology has had 40 years of steady influence on social and political movements throughout the world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PKK leader Abdullah Ocalan started reading Bookchin at the beginning of his prison exile in the early 2000’s, bringing Bookchin’s works to his lawyers as recommended reading for the rest of the PKK. In 2004, Ocalan recognized himself in a letter to Bookchin as his “student”, and was in the process of establishing his own theories modeled on Bookchin’s ideas. In 2006, the PKK began organizing Democratic Autonomy, an administrative system of civic councils to statelessly govern North Kurdistan. Democratic Autonomy would become an important antecedent for the cantons in Rojava, as well as for the confederal projects currently being set up within the Turkish state by the HDP (Democratic Union Party).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Autonomy is one of the first revolutionary Left project to exercise power under an explicitly confederalist agenda. Although it did not practice direct democracy, it did mark the 21st century’s first serious attempt to approach the municipality—not the nation or the state—as the authentic unit of governance. Unlike traditional Marxism, which reduced politics to economics and thus failed to offer democratic solutions, this approach brings economic decisions under the umbrella of communal decision-making. And unlike traditional anarchism, which avoided the question of institutional power altogether, this approach seeks to popularize power and render it transparent. Democratic Autonomy, the Rojava cantons, and other projects under democratic confederalism are steps toward creating (however imperfectly) a new realm of human activity characterized by free deliberation, debate, and the exercise of reason.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;freedom&amp;#95;and&amp;#95;organic&amp;#95;society&quot;&gt;Freedom and Organic Society&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt; The PKK never regarded the Kurdish question as a mere problem of ethnicity or nationhood. Rather, we believed, it was the project of liberating society and democratizing it.” – Abdullah Ocalan, 2011. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intellectual commentators of the Kurdish revolutionary movement often focus on the juncture of principles and practice, looking no farther back in history than the establishment of the PKK in the 1970’s. But in order to understand how (or rather why) these principles came to emerge, one must use a deeply historical and dialectical lens. Social ecology offers one crucial piece of that puzzle. Through Ocalan’s interpretations, it has offered Kurds a radical new framework for asserting their role in the history of human liberation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In The Ecology of Freedom, Bookchin accounts for the historical development of the concept of freedom. He identifies the beginning of this development in the earliest human settlements of Mesopotamia, what is now modern day Kurdistan. Nearly 12,000 years ago, human beings initiated a decisive step in social development, undertaking the project of living together with more than they could carry on their backs. This project presented vast new challenges for organizing and making sense of the world. Thus Mesopotamia is where we find the earliest instances of written language, mathematics, architecture, and agriculture. It is also, Bookchin recognized, where we find the beginnings of the struggle between ideologies of freedom and domination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bookchin points to the cuneiform word amargi (“return to the mother”), which first appears nearly 5,000 years ago in juxtaposition to the newly oppressive conditions under the Sumerian state. Organic society, he argues, had no previous word for the concept of ‘freedom’, just as fish might have no word for ‘water’. This conflict between freedom and unfreedom has stayed with society to the present day. Indeed, the revolutionary challenge we face today is that of pushing the development of freedom forward, making freedom, rather than hierarchy, the dominant social principle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just a few short days within a Kurdish household reveal that the organic society upon which the earliest states imposed themselves never fully vanished. From oral traditions of epic song to meaningful practices of naming children (I spent time with a little girl named Amargi, for instance), Kurds have retained ancient forms of egalitarian and organic social life since the Neolithic. Like many organic or so-called indigenous peoples, traditional Kurdish kinship networks are vast and intricate. Once, while explaining the role of tribal groups in the Kobane defense, Sherhad turned to me and asked, “How many cousins do you have?” “About 20,” I replied, “I have a big Catholic family on my father’s side,” to which he responded, “Counting both sides, I have over 200.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many of the Ocalanist revolutionaries I spoke to described their struggle as one of organic society against authoritarian society. They articulated a clear sense that not only capitalism and statist forces produced ISIS, but also the mentality of hierarchical society itself. However, it was also emphasized that the purpose of democratic modernity is not simply to revive organic society. Rather, it is to revive the social and ethical aspects of organic society and weave them with the ethical principles gained by Western enlightenment. At the same time, it advocates the use of reason to work out the unethical aspects of traditional Kurdish society (tribal rivalries, for example), while also refusing the cold scientism and positivism of the west. Such a synthesis moves us into a new stage in the development of freedom, one which Ocalan calls “democratic civilization” and which Bookchin referred to simply as a free society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;the&amp;#95;power&amp;#95;of&amp;#95;a&amp;#95;coherent&amp;#95;narrative&quot;&gt;The Power of a Coherent Narrative&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;By focusing on hierarchy instead of class, Bookchin became the first Leftist thinker to offer a coherent, meaningful framework for the liberation struggles in the Middle East. His narrative implies that a revolutionary movement in Kurdistan is a struggle at the material origin of institutional hierarchy itself. Although such a localized struggle cannot automatically release hierarchy’s tight grip over rest of the world, it does powerfully illustrate the full scope of the revolutionary task at hand. In this way, the Kurdish freedom movement is not only influenced by social ecology, it also enriches that perspective and articulates it further. The human beings who live at the material origins of institutional hierarchy, and who have maintained organic ways of life there for millennia, are now answering the call to establish the positive conditions of a free society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many westerners are baffled by the determination of PYD and YPJ fighters, their ability to simultaneously withstand multiple attacks of genocidal violence and maintain a commitment to the praxis of anti-authoritarianism. In Kurdistan I found myself humbled by the seriousness with which revolutionaries went about their project. Yet from a social ecological perspective I was also able to grasp that the Kurdish movement is infused with a deep sense of purpose, a knowledge that they have a catalytic role to play in world history. I was reminded of one of the passages in Bookchin’s essay, The Communalist Project:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Communalists] do not delude themselves that the state will view with equanimity their attempts to replace professionalized power with popular power…That the new popular-assemblyist municipal confederations will embody a dual power against the state that becomes a source of growing political tension is obvious. Either a Communalist movement will be radicalized by this tension and will resolutely face all its consequences, or it will surely sink into a morass of compromises that absorb it back into the social order it once sought to change. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clearly Kurds have selected the former path. What remains to be answered is how will we respond? Will we resolutely face the consequences of a coherent, historicized revolutionary vision, or will we continue to slowly fade into a morass of ever-diminishing compromises? Kurds have found—indeed, have chosen—their place in the development of human freedom. What is ours?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accessed January 24th, 2018 from the &lt;a href='http://social-ecology.org/wp/2015/06/social-ecology-kurdistan-the-origins-of-freedom/'&gt;Institute for Social Ecology website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
Eleanor Finley
</author>
<pubDate>
Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
/posts/2018-01-23-popular-assemblies/
</guid>
<link>
/posts/2018-01-23-popular-assemblies/
</link>
<title>
Popular Assemblies and Confederations
</title>
<description>
 &lt;p&gt;Communalism is an ideology and a political movement, which aims for a direct democracy.  It abandons capitalism as ecologically unsustainable and inhumane. However communalists do not seek an alternative by strengthening the state or taking over state power for themselves, but from a social order that rises from taking part in local popular assemblies and libertarian associations based on them.  Communalism provides a clear and practical proposal for political institutions and praxis that enable social freedom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;direct&amp;#95;democracy&quot;&gt;Direct democracy&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to communalists, all political power should belong to local popular assemblies. True democracy can only be accomplished if people take part in open assemblies, where they can meet each other face-to-face and create social forms of action together.  Every member of a community should have an equal right to propose matters to their neighbourhoods popular assembly to decide upon and also to voice their opinions on them. No act is democratically justified if it is not directly proposed, discussed and decided on by the people – and not by any kind of  representative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Managing these jobs can, however, be left for committees or other forms of workgroups that execute the decisions of the assembly under their close scrutiny.  Membership in committees and workgroups, and also other jobs and responsibilities, can be rotated  regularly so that power doesn’t accumulate on omission to a few based on their  “expertise” or knowledge.  All members of a community don’t, of course, have to take part in all deciding about all issues, but all will have an equal possibility to take part in matters that are important to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;decentralizing&amp;#95;cities&quot;&gt;Decentralizing cities&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The size of cities and municipalities is crucial to fulfilling communalist ideals of civic democracy and governance of cities and municipalities by their members.  Modern metropolitan cities have to be, in the end, decentralized to smaller municipalities and communities. This also has sound ecological reasons for it.  Physical decentralization of cities will of course take a long time, but they can be decentralized institutionally before that. Popular assemblies can at first work as networks in block, neighbourhood and city levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;municipalization&amp;#95;of&amp;#95;the&amp;#95;economy&quot;&gt;Municipalization of the economy&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communalists propose that the economy should be municipalized and all privately owned land and factories and other production facilities should be moved to joint ownership by the municipality’s citizens.  Decisions about economic functions will be made by all members of the municipality in assemblies.  This would mean that economy as a whole will be brought into political decision-making and also that single factories or farms will no longer be competing entities.  In assemblies people would not only belong to their own profession with their own conflicting interests, but they would work for the benefit of the whole community. This way a basis could be created for an economy of purely ethical reasoning, where everyone would give according to their abilities and receive according to their needs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;confederalism&quot;&gt;Confederalism&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;All economic activity or decision-making  doesn’t need – or have– to be limited to areas where people can congregate to meet in assemblies. Communalists propose a confederation as democratical and libertarian municipal alliances. It is a network of administrative councils whose members are selected face-to-face in assemblies. The delegates can be recalled and changed at any moment and they are responsible to the assemblies that have chosen them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assemblies also carefully regulate the delegates and give guidelines to their action.  In fact they are more messengers of assemblies rather then representatives, since representatives make decisions for the communities that they represent.  Decision-making and making policy decisions will be solely the right of the assemblies. Only administration and coordination are the responsibilities of confederal councils.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If members of a confederation cannot get to a agreement through their delegates, a confederation-wide general election can be held, where the common policy of municipalities will be decided.  When creating a confederation there can be an agreement among members that functions as a sort of a constitution for the confederation and that defines every member community’s rights. For example how they can resign from the confederation and what kind of issues can be decided in whole confederation-wide general elections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An agreement like this would on one hand secure the rights of communities and the people who live in them against the arbitrariness of the majority opinion and also would make possible action in the case of a single community polluting other communities areas.  Also confederalism would prevent local communities from relapsing to parochialism. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also economic cooperation should be expanded to cover the whole confederation. ideally, communities would combine their strengths in local confederal networks that would join even larger – ultimately even worldwide – networks where production and distribution is planned according to the needs of a community and their possiblities for production. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;assemblies&amp;#95;as&amp;#95;a&amp;#95;force&amp;#95;for&amp;#95;change&quot;&gt;Assemblies as a force for change&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of the most important methods when striving for communalism are starting local assemblies, strengthening and making their power legally binding and radically democratizing existing municipal institutions. Local assemblies should also create confederalist networks with other communities, so that the movement can rise to be national and even international.  This way directly democratic political institutions would exist already before abandoning the old social order and a relapse to oligarchy would be unlikely after a revolution.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The functioning of assemblies could create many needed reforms in people’s lives already when political power officially belongs to the state and state-like municipal structures. When they develop assemblies will most likely come to a conflict with state institutions and the capitalist economy, because power cannot exist simultaneously belong to both the state and corporations that govern the economy and the people in directly democratic institutions. This way a revolutionary tension will form, that causes assemblies to take all political power to themselves and their confederation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to starting assemblies communalists also favor co-ops and other co-operative forms of educational alternative economy.  However these should be regarded as mostly educational, because staying alive in the market and growing to challenge capitalism is quite unlikely. Rather these islands of an alternative economy must copy ever more practices from regular companies and they must adapt to existing economy according to Its terms.  True struggle is fought over political power that must also be used to force economic activity to become part of assemblies’ direct governance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
Jyri Jaakkola
</author>
<pubDate>
Tue, 23 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
/posts/2018-01-10-libertarian-municipalism/
</guid>
<link>
/posts/2018-01-10-libertarian-municipalism/
</link>
<title>
Libertarian Municipalism
</title>
<description>
 &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt; Libertarian municipalism is a political program developed by libertarian socialist theorist Murray Bookchin, to create democratic citizens' assemblies in towns and urban neighborhoods. The assemblies in these free municipalities join together to replace the state with a directly democratic confederation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libertarian_municipalism'&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Murray Bookchin, an American eco-anarchist who became a self-styled “communalist,” proposed the idea of “libertarian municipalism” — a notion that relied on the development of confederal political structures as a counter-power to the centralized nation-state. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In The Next Revolution, Bookchin broadly outlines a program and rough design of libertarian municipalism and anti-state confederalism of cities and towns. Within cities, he discusses the possibilities of advancing a minimum policy program and maximum program. The former meets demands for improved welfare of residents and generates pockets of direct participation and empowerment that can serve as stepping stones to more wholesale institutional transformation. The maximum program is one in which people power is at the center of this institutional transformation: here, decision-making power is transferred from municipal-level representative institutions to that of direct-democratic assemblies. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;For Bookchin, one approach to achieving both the minimum and maximum program is to “electorally” engage “in a potentially important center of power — the municipal council,” so as to “compel it to create legislatively potent neighborhood assemblies.” More specifically, Bookchin writes that “communalists do not hesitate to run candidates in municipal elections who, if elected, would use what real power their offices confer to legislate popular assemblies into existence.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taken a step further, Bookchin writes that “a confederalist alternative would be based on a network of policy-making popular assemblies with recallable deputies to local and regional confederal councils — councils whose sole function, I must emphasize, would be to adjudicate differences and undertake strictly administrative tasks.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Janet Biehl, Bookchin’s longtime intellectual partner, writes that “city charters or other constitutions would be altered to legitimate the power of the assemblies in local self-government.” Many on the Left — including anarchists — are paying closer attention to the role of constitutions. One may even take this further and look at possibilities for advancing a post-state monetary system that is consistent with confederalism, such as that outlined by Nathan Cedric Tankus. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whatever the complications might be in terms of the relationship between policymaking and administration, representation and direct participation and other issues, Bookchin’s broader point is that municipalities can be the site of institutional transformation and the material bases for the construction of a viable counter-power. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://roarmag.org/essays/us-anti-fascism-municipalism/'&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further Reading:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://roarmag.org/essays/us-anti-fascism-municipalism/'&gt;Is America ready for a municipalist movement?&lt;/a&gt; Roar Magazine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/murray-bookchin-libertarian-municipalism-an-overview'&gt;Libertarian Municipalism: An Overview&lt;/a&gt; by Murray Bookchin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://dwardmac.pitzer.edu/Anarchist_Archives/bookchin/libmuni.html'&gt;Libertarian Municipalism: The New Municipal Agenda&lt;/a&gt; by Murray Bookchin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.biehlonbookchin.com/lib-municipalism/'&gt;Libertarian Municipalism Keynote Speech&lt;/a&gt; by Janet Biehl&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
Janet Biehl and Murray Bookchin
</author>
<pubDate>
Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
/posts/2018-01-04-what-is-capitalism/
</guid>
<link>
/posts/2018-01-04-what-is-capitalism/
</link>
<title>
What is Capitalism?
</title>
<description>
 &lt;p&gt; From long-time ISE faculty member, Peter Staudenmeier, written for the Lexicon pamphlet series sponsored by the Institute for Anarchist Studies. This was originally posted in March 2014 and revised in August 2015:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In ancient myths of paradise, people lived in boundless plenty without work or want. The fruits of the earth were freely available to all and no labor was necessary. If life under capitalism is a far cry from paradise, it is nonetheless beholden to its own myths of work, prosperity, and progress. Understanding what the world was like before the rise of capitalism, and envisioning a different world beyond the capitalist reality we live in today, calls for an examination of its myths and the structures on which those myths are built.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Capitalism usually presents itself as an economic system, a way of organizing the production and distribution of goods and services, of wealth and welfare, of material gain and loss. But capitalism is more than an economic system, it is a form of society: A society in which the economic has taken precedence over the social. Under capitalism, economic necessities become more important than basic social relationships – finding a job and keeping it can be more pressing than creating a fulfilling life together with friends and companions and loved ones; figuring out how to pay the rent or maintain the mortgage or make sure there’s food on the table wins out over exploring what we have in common; worrying about who’ll take care of us when we’re too old to work gets in the way of taking care of each other here and now. W hat is best for me individually becomes more vital than what is best for the communities I am part of, than what is best for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we find ourselves thinking this way, it is not because we are inherently selfish beings. That notion of natural self-interest and acquisitiveness is one of the major myths of modern capitalism. Human societies have evolved myriad ways of arranging their economic interactions, many of them based squarely on communal rather than individual standards of well-being. They aren’t always liberatory, of course, but they do indicate that capitalism’s peculiar preoccupation with concern for oneself over others is not built in to human nature. And most people don’t get all that far under capitalism, economically speaking, no matter how much we focus on our own needs and wants. Though the free market continually holds out the promise of a better life for all, the promise generally becomes reality for only a few.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Viewed in this context, capitalism is by no means historically inevitable. It isn’t part of the fabric of the universe and it isn’t a consequence of the laws of physics. It is not an innate attribute of human existence. It is not, as it pretends to be, the natural state of economic affairs. Capitalism is a social artifact, something created and maintained by people, by our actions and inactions, whether deliberate or inadvertent, whether malevolent or well-meaning. It arose in particular places at specific times under distinctive conditions. It has a history, though admirers of capitalism sometimes like to portray it as timeless. Like everything historical, it has both beginnings and an end. If we made it, we can unmake it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That means understanding how it functions. To do this we can draw on both theory and practice, incorporating the lessons learned from critical analyses of the basic structures of capitalism as well as the legacies of organized opposition to those structures. W e can make use of the insights generated by radical social movements throughout the long history of emancipatory struggles against capitalism. Many of these struggles were led by workers in class-based movements resisting the growing power of capital. Others were made up of peasants or artisans, and some were community-based movements defending popular institutions from encroachment by an advancing capitalist system. The participants in these struggles disagreed about how to make sense of capitalism’s seemingly senseless rules, but we can distill a series of key concepts from their experiences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of these oppositional movements and their assessment of a world transformed according to capitalist imperatives, the core features of capitalism as an economic system and as a society can be characterized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;commodity&amp;#95;production&amp;#95;and&amp;#95;exchange.&quot;&gt;Commodity production and exchange.&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commodities are the fundamental unit of capitalist societies, as the cell is the fundamental unit of the body. Under full-fledged capitalism a commodity can be just about anything – something useful and necessary, something harmful and pointless, something rare or common, something intangible and ephemeral. W hat makes an item or an idea or an action a commodity is not some intrinsic quality of the thing itself, but its status as an object of exchange. In its simplest form, a commodity is a good or a service that is produced in order to be exchanged. It is valuable not primarily for what it is, but for what price it can fetch when bought or sold, what can be gained by exchanging it for other commodities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;markets.&quot;&gt;Markets.&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mechanism through which commodities are exchanged is the market, a forum in which buyers and sellers compete for advantage. Historically markets were subject to social constraints: typically located in circumscribed areas, limited to certain times of the day or week or year, tempered by ethical stipulations. Many human societies assigned markets a deliberately subordinate position in communal life and delineated clear boundaries within which markets were allowed to operate. This changed with the ascendance of capitalism. In an ideal capitalist world, markets and their competitive dynamic no longer heed social limitations but are ubiquitous and unfettered; they are everywhere all the time. Though championed for their supposed efficiency, markets are frequently models of extraordinary waste and inefficiency. In their capitalist form markets have a tendency to permeate all relationships and all dimensions of social life, extending far beyond the immediate economic realm and turning neighbors into rivals, colleagues into competitors, allies into adversaries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;property&amp;#95;as&amp;#95;private&amp;#95;investment.&quot;&gt;Property as private investment.&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through the processes of commodity production and market exchange, more and more aspects of human life and the natural world are reduced to assets that can and must be owned. W ealth comes from the earth and its creatures and from the work of human hands and minds, and there are countless forms in which it can be created, discovered, and shared. Many of these forms have been communal, collective, cooperative. Capitalism imposes one form as paramount: private ownership of resources. In contemporary industrial capitalist societies this type of private property takes the shape of entrepreneurs who own a business, shareholders or investors who own a corporation, landlords who own real estate, speculators who own stock or trade debt and credit and abstract commodities existing only in notional form. The driving force behind this kind of ownership is profit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;exploited&amp;#95;labor.&quot;&gt;Exploited labor.&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most people in capitalist contexts don’t own assets that earn profit, and have to sell their time and effort in order to make a living. Selling your ability to work in exchange for a paycheck is known as wage labor, the component of capitalism with which most of us are intimately familiar. A division of labor between groups of people doing different tasks is not peculiar to capitalism, but in combination with commodity production, the predominance of the market, and private ownership of economic resources, the exploitation of labor means that the people who actually produce the goods and services that keep the system running have little say in how the things they produce are made and distributed. Those decisions are normally the prerogative of owners, executives, and managers, whose directives are supposed to be carried out by workers. W hen the system works the way it is designed, products end up in the hands of consumers divorced from any connection with or knowledge of the producers or their conditions of work, from mass manufacturing to the provision of services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the basis of these intertwined core features, capitalism has achieved remarkable levels of economic innovation and equally remarkable levels of ecological and social destructiveness. W hat drives both its accomplishments and its devastation is a constant requirement for accumulation, for increasing returns on investment, for profits that can be put back into circulation in order to yield even greater profit. Ever-expanding material reward is the carrot that entices capitalist ambitions, accompanied by the stick of potential economic ruin. W hile its operations are baroquely complex and often inscrutable, its underlying principles are starkly straightforward. This accounts for capitalism’s conspicuous flexibility, the capacity to accommodate itself to widely different social and cultural contexts. It also accounts for the profoundly alienated relationships at the heart of capitalist society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because capitalism is built around recurrent crises, economic and otherwise, it has always sparked dissatisfaction and resistance. From anarchists to marxists, from cooperative movements to anti-colonial struggles, diverse groups and individuals have contested the regime of capital for generations. For those of us fundamentally opposed to capitalism, it is crucial to keep in mind the political ambivalence of discontent with capitalist norms. History is littered with false alternatives to an inhumane and unsustainable system. Stalinism, to choose one all too recognizable example, is not a compelling replacement for free market nostrums. Many populists and fascists also oppose capitalism, based often enough on the alluring but deceptive paradigm of hardworking producers versus parasitic financiers. There are numerous authoritarian and right-wing versions of anti-capitalist sentiment. W e need to remember this if we don’t want to end up in a future that is even worse than the capitalist present. The challenge is to come up with a comprehensive critical analysis of what is wrong with capitalism and a plausible array of alternative social institutions that could supplant it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A helpful step toward that goal is to ask questions without easy answers. W hat is it about capitalism that we oppose? Its outsize impact on our lives, our character, our bodies, our planet? Its privileging of multinational corporations and millionaires? Its cosmopolitanism and its corrosive effect on traditional mores? Or is it alienation and exploitation that we reject? And what are we working toward? A more smoothly functioning liberal state that will provide for all? Local self-sufficiency and regional autarky? Planning bureaucracies and legislated equality? Environmental enterprise and reduced consumption? Neighborhood markets and family farms and mom and pop stores? Or do we want a genuinely anti-capitalist alternative, structurally antagonistic to hierarchy and domination, to profit and property, whatever their scale or scope?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beyond decisive questions like these, there are many other problems to be thought through and worked out. Capitalism is not as all-encompassing as it appears; non- capitalist relationships exist within and alongside the dominant economy and society. And as central as production is to economic endeavors, reproduction and care are what make our lives possible, while the pleasure of personal and collective creation for its own sake, regardless of utility, can make our lives worth living. Indeed the very notion of ‘the economy’ as a separate sphere of social life is itself a legacy of the historical emergence of capitalism. Today’s shifting affiliations linking capitalism to the state, to white supremacy, to patriarchy, to racial and gender and other hierarchies are not an implacable constant but always in flux, with oppressive as well as subversive potentials. The crushing weight of capital distorts any image of a life after capitalism, but the possibilities of transcending its bitter strictures are entirely real. They are ours to explore, ours to construct, and ours to share.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;about&amp;#95;the&amp;#95;author:&amp;#95;peter&amp;#95;staudenmaier&quot;&gt;About the Author: Peter Staudenmaier&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peter Staudenmaier is a social ecologist and historian who has been involved with the Institute for Social Ecology since 1989. He has been an active participant in the anarchist movement, the green movement, and the cooperative movement in the United States and Germany for over two decades. He lives in Wisconsin and teaches history at Marquette University.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<author>
Peter Staudenmaier
</author>
<pubDate>
Thu, 04 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
